<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Gia-Alexander/HIST630/master/GESchematron.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Gia-Alexander/HIST630/master/RebuiltODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TEI Encoding of the Introduction to Class 17 from <bibl><title> Volume III of the
                     Official Catalogue of the Great Exhibition of the Works of Industry of All
                     Nations <date when="1851">1851</date>(4 vols.),</title><biblScope unit="page"
                     from="536" to="537"/></bibl></title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Gia O. Alexander</authority>
            <pubPlace>College Station, TX</pubPlace>
            <date>Fall 2019</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                  Licence and may be freely reused with attribution.</licence>
               <p>The primary source material for this project is available in the public domain at
                  archive.org.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the publication of the source work. Introductions to sections of
               the catalogue containing information about about writing substrates, implements and
               accessories excerpted from <bibl><title>Volume III of the Official Catalogue of the
                     Great Exhibition of the Works of Industry of All Nations <date when="1851"
                        >1851</date></title> (4 vols.) from <publisher>Archive.org</publisher>,
                  scanned from <placeName ref="#HarvardCollege">Harvard College Library</placeName>
                  by <publisher>Google Books</publisher>. <idno type="URI">
                     https://archive.org/details/officialcatalog06unkngoog/page/n14</idno></bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <category xml:id="Paper">
                  <catDesc> PAPER, PRINTING, AND BOOKBINDING </catDesc>
                  <category xml:id="BulkPaper">
                     <catDesc>A. Paper in the raw slate as it leaves the mill, such as Brown Paper,
                        Millboards, Printing, Writing, and Drawing Papen, &amp;c.</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Stationery">
                     <catDesc>B. Articles of Stationery, as Envelopes, Lace Papers, Fancy Papers,
                        Ornamented and Glazed Papers, Sealing-wai, Wafers, inks of ail kinds,
                        &amp;c.
                           <idno type="URI">https://hobancards.com/stationery-of-the-victorian-era</idno>
                     </catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="CardStock">
                     <catDesc>C. Pasteboards, Cards, &amp;c. ; and Scaleboard Boxes, Cartonnerie,
                        &amp;c.</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Printing">
                     <catDesc>D. Printing, not including printing as a fine art, and Printing Inks
                        and Varnishes ; Bookbinding in cloth, velvet, vellum, &amp;c. ; Fancy Books,
                        Portfolios, Desks, &amp;c,</catDesc>
                  </category>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="class" n="3.17">
            <head type="class"> PAPER, PRINTING, AND BOOKBINDING. </head>
            <div type="intro">
               <head type="subTitle"> INTRODUCTION. </head>

               <p xml:id="a17"> Paper of every description, printing and bookbinding, with the
                  miscellaneous articles connected with correspondence, and useful and ornamental
                  stationery, form the subjects of the present Class. The manufacture of these
                  articles—ministering not to the personal or domestic wants of mankind, fit much as
                  to their intellectual requirements—is one of annual increase of which is
                  coexistent with the diffusion of knowledge. And it may be truly said, that,
                  morally and intellectually considered, the present Class relates to a species of
                  industry exercising indirectly a more extensive influence over social economy than
                  any of those into which this Exhibition has been subdivided. Books, it has been
                  said, carry the productions of the human mind over the whole« world, and may be
                  truly called the raw materials of every kind of science and art, and of all social
                  improvement. The Sub-Classes are as follows : — A. Paper in the raw slate as it
                  leaves the mill, such as Brown Paper, Millboards, Printing, Writing, and Drawing
                  Papen, &amp;c. ; B. Articles of Stationery, as Envelopes, Lace Papers, Fancy
                  Papers, Ornamented and Glazed Papers, Sealing-wai, Wafers, inks of ail kinds,
                  &amp;c. ; C. Pasteboards, Cards, &amp;c. ; and Scaleboard Boxes, Cartonnerie,
                  &amp;c. ; D. Printing, not including printing as a fine art, and Printing Inks and
                  Varnishes ; Bookbinding in cloth, velvet, vellum, &amp;c. ; Fancy Books,
                  Portfolios, Desks, &amp;c, </p>

               <p xml:id="b17"> The position occupied in the Building is in the North side of the
                  Western Main Avenue ; and the Areas included are F, 27 to 29, G. H. I. J. 26 and
                  27. Rather more than 200 exhibitors appear to represent this Class in its various
                  branches of industry. </p>

               <p xml:id="c17"> The localities from whence the articles exhibited have been sent are
                  much less restricted than in preceding Classes. Many of the exhibitors appear in
                  the capacity of producers of <objectName type="Stationery">small articles for fancy purposes</objectName> ; and as these are
                  obviously capable of being made at home, requiring taste and minute skill rather
                  than mechanical power for their manufacture, the places from which they have been
                  forwarded for exhibition have not the special interest attaching to great
                  producing towns or cities, where thousands of machines and operatives are all
                  occupied in one department of manufacture. From the <placeName ref="#London">metropolis,</placeName> however, where a
                  large demand for such articles exists, the great proportion of them are derived.
                     <placeName ref="#London">London</placeName> also represents most largely the
                  enormous printing resources of this country. Hut of these, as specimens only of
                  single works can appear, but a faint idea can be gained from the examples
                  exhibited, In one of the greatest establishments of the <placeName ref="#London"
                     >Metropolis</placeName> twenty <objectName type="Printing">machines</objectName> are constantly occupied, each of which
                  is capable of throwing off from 3,000 to 4,000 impressions per hour, and in
                  addition a large number of printing <objectName type="Printing">machines</objectName> for fine work are employed. These
                  great printing establishments resemble very closely the large manufactories of
                  other districts, only their origination differs with the peculiar nature of the
                  manufacture, if the mechanical production of printed books may be so termed. </p>

               <p xml:id="d17"> <objectName type="BulkPaper">Paper</objectName>, more legitimately reckoned among manufactures than printing,
                  has a certain limitation to districts for particular kinds. Considerably more is
                  made in <placeName ref="#England">England</placeName> than in <placeName
                     ref="#Scotland">Scotland</placeName> or <placeName ref="#Ireland"
                     >Ireland</placeName>. <placeName ref="#Kent">Kent</placeName> is celebrated for
                  its fine writing and drawing papers. From <placeName ref="#Lancashire"
                     >Lancashire</placeName>, <placeName ref="#Berkshire">Berkshire</placeName>,
                     <placeName ref="#Hereford">Hereford</placeName>, and <placeName
                     ref="#Derbyshire">Derbyshire</placeName>, papers of various kinds are supplied.
                  The quantity of paper annually manufactured in <placeName ref="#England"
                     >England</placeName> two years ago amounted to 132,132,657 lbs. ; in <date
                     when="1834">1834</date>, it was little more than half that quantity. In <date
                     when="1839">1839</date>, it was estimated that the quantity used, if equally
                  divided among the population, would have been about three pounds and three-
                  quarters for each individual. </p>

               <p xml:id="e17"> A variety of mechanical improvements, both in the production of
                  <objectName type="BulkPaper">paper</objectName> and in that of printed <objectName type="Printing">books</objectName>, has been introduced of late. In the
                  manufacture of paper the substitution of machine for hand labour has been attended
                  with the most momentous results. In <date when="1801">1801</date>, the price of a
                  ream of paper of a particular description was 36s. ; in <date when="1834"
                     >1843</date>, the same paper could be purchased for rather less than half this
                  sum. In <date when="1721">1721</date>, it is estimated that 300,000 reams of paper were annually produced
                  in <placeName ref="#GreatBritain">Great Britain</placeName>. In <date when="1843"
                     >1841</date>, 97,105,550 lbs. were made in the <placeName ref="#UnitedKingdom"
                     >United Kingdom</placeName> ; the total annual value is at present not far
                  short of two millions sterling. Much of tbc increase thus exhibited is due to the
                  introduction of mechanical power ; but the fiscal regulations upon this branch of
                  industry, which were formerly extremely oppressive, having been removed to some
                  extent, another cause of increased production and consumption is thus superadded.
                  Paper may, however, be likewise regarded as a chemical product, as it is certain
                  that a large amount of chemical knowledge has been successfully combined with
                  mechanical skill in its preparation. By the cumulative forces of chemical
                  processes and mechanical <objectName type="Printing">instruments</objectName>, the most refuse matter thus becomes
                  converted into a white and pure material. As an evidence of the enormous length of
                  paper produced by mechanical power, two great <objectName type="BulkPaper">rolls</objectName> are exhibited —one is 750
                  yards long, the other 2500 yards in length. </p>

               <p xml:id="f17"> The application of improved <objectName type="Printing">machinery</objectName> to printing is also of recent
                  date, and has been attended with results of great moment. Progress is still made
                  in this direction, and in a preceding Class will be found a more detailed account
                  of the introduction of an entirely new principle in printing (the vertical), the
                  application of which for the rapid multiplication of newspapers is extending. By
                  this arrangement, the vertical, the power of production is only limited by the
                  size of the machine. </p>

               <p xml:id="g17"> Among many interesting specimens of <objectName type="Printing">typography</objectName>, those which exhibit
                  the production of books in other countries, by type cast in <placeName
                     ref="#England">England</placeName>, will attract notice. The Holy Scriptures
                  are exhibited in one hundred and fifty different languages—a noble evidence of the
                  highest application of industry to the enlightenment and welfare of mankind.
                  Beautiful specimens of the bookbinder's art are likewise shown. </p>

               <p xml:id="h17"> An envelope-folding machine, placed at the side of the Main Avenue,
                  is a striking instance of the successful application or mechanical movements to
                  the performance of the most delicate and complicated actions. By this machine,
                  which would in strictness appear to belong to a preceding Class, the movements of
                  the hand of the folder are not only exactly imitated, but the result is more
                  accurate and certain, and the power of pro- duction is very largely increased. </p>

               <p xml:id="i17"> The peculiar interest which attaches to the objects in this Class,
                  as the most powerful agents in the social and intellectual improvement of man,
                  cannot fail to be awakened by the most casual inspection. Paper, printing and
                  bookbinding, are, however, only the <objectName type="BulkPaper">raw material</objectName>, the application and reproduction
                  of which is dependent upon the powers of the mind, not on those of matter. —
                     <persName ref="#RE">R. E.</persName>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
