<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TEI Encoding of the Introduction to Class 29 from <bibl><title> Volume III of the
                     Official Catalogue of the Great Exhibition of the Works of Industry of All
                     Nations <date when="1851">1851</date>(4 vols.),</title><biblScope unit="page"
                     from="789" to="789"/></bibl></title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Gia O. Alexander</authority>
            <pubPlace>College Station, TX</pubPlace>
            <date>Fall 2019</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                  Licence and may be freely reused with attribution.</licence>
               <p>The primary source material for this project is available in the public domain at
                  archive.org.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the publication of the source work. Introductions to sections of
               the catalogue containing information about about writing substrates, implements and
               accessories excerpted from <bibl><title>Volume III of the Official Catalogue of the
                     Great Exhibition of the Works of Industry of All Nations <date
                        when="1851">1851</date></title> (4 vols.) from
                  <publisher>Archive.org</publisher>, scanned from <placeName ref="#HarvardCollege">Harvard College
                     Library</placeName> by <publisher>Google Books</publisher>. <idno type="URI">
                     https://archive.org/details/officialcatalog06unkngoog/page/n14</idno></bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <category xml:id="SmallWares">
                  <catDesc>
                     MISCELLANEOUS MANUFACTURES AND SMALL WARES
                  </catDesc>
                  <category xml:id="Perfume">
                     <catDesc>A. Perfumery and Soap</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="BoxesCases">
                     <catDesc>B. Articles for personal use, as Writing-desks, Dressing-cases. Work-boxes, when not exhibited in connection with
                        precious metals and travelling wear generally
                        <idno type="URI">https://mostlyboxesantiques.com/epages/cbfa87b3-21bd-409d-ac51-11c8ded24597.sf/en_GB/?ObjectPath=/Shops/cbfa87b3-21bd-409d-ac51-11c8ded24597/Categories/28</idno>
                     </catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="FakeFlowers">
                     <catDesc>C. Artificial Flowers</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Candles">
                     <catDesc>D. Candles, and other means of giving light</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Confectionery">
                     <catDesc>E. Confectionery of all kinds</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Beads">
                     <catDesc>F. Beads and Toys, when not of hardware. Fans, &amp;c.</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Umbrellas">
                     <catDesc>G. Umbrellas, Parasols,Walking-sticks, &amp;c.</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Fishing">
                     <catDesc>H. Fishing-tackle of all kinds, Archery, &amp;c.</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="WalkingCanes">
                     <catDesc>I. Canes of all kinds</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="MiscSmallWares">
                     <catDesc>J. Other miscellaneous manufactures</catDesc>
                  </category>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="class" n="3.29">
            <head type="class"> MISCELLANEOUS MANUFACTURES AND SMALL WARES</head>
            <div type="intro">
               <head type="subTitle"> INTRODUCTION. </head>

               <p xml:id="a29"> The miscellaneous character of the objects included in this Class renders it
                  difficult to convey a precise idea of its general import, or of the distinguishing
                  features of the articles exhibited under it. Small wares may be taken to
                  comprehend a very large variety of articles, and miscellaneous manufactures
                  necessarily include a similar variety. The following feature may, however, be
                  considered to characterise the articles brought together under this Class, that
                  they are principally, though not exclusively, related to the minor points in the
                  domestic economy of society. And this will be evident on examination of the
                  Sub-Classes into which it is divided. </p>

               <p xml:id="b29"> These are as follow : — A. Perfumery and Soap ; B. Articles for personal use, as
                  Writing-desks, Dressing-cases. Work-boxes, when not exhibited in connection with
                  precious metals and travelling wear generally ; C. Artificial Flowers ; D.
                  Candles, and other means of giving light ; E. Confectionery of all kinds ; F.
                  Beads and Toys, when not of hardware. Fans, &amp;c. ; G. Umbrellas, Parasols,
                  Walking-sticks, &amp;c. ; H. Fishing-tackle of all kinds, Archery, &amp;c. ; I. Canes
                  of all kinds; J. Other miscellaneous manufactures. </p>

               <p xml:id="c29"> These articles are placed in the North Transept Gallery. Included, however, among
                  the miscellaneous objects are two valuable and important collections which
                  scarcely appear to come under precise recognition in this Class. These collections
                  are of the imports of the towns of Liverpool and Hull. They have been arranged
                  with great care, and present an excellent picture of the staple articles of trade,
                  and of many of the less important ones, constantly received as imitations from
                  abroad by these flourishing sea-ports. The list of the Liverpool Collection has
                  been inserted in the body of this Catalogue, in consequence of the value attaching
                  to accurate statistical local information. This list bos undergone careful
                  scientific revision, and its generic expressions may be taken as, on the whole,
                  accurate. </p>

               <p xml:id="d29"> The manufacture of soaps and candles is the only one of great commercial
                  importance to which this Class has relation. The employment of soap in many
                  processes of manufacture, in addition to the intense demand created by domestic
                  necessities, render its production on the great scale proportionally interesting.
                  The rate of increase in the quantity produced, during the lost half-century, may
                  be estimated from the fact that in <date when="1801">1801</date>, 52,947,037 lbs. of soap were consumed ;
                  and, in <date when="1849">1849</date>, the annual consumption amounted to 197,632,280 lbs. The
                  quantity per head amounted, in the latter year, to 971 lbs. annually ; in the
                  former to 484 lbs. But which of the increase of consumption is to be attributed to
                  the development of manufacture in which this substance is used for various
                  purposes. It is a remarkable fact that, during the same period, the number of
                  licensed makers of soap has decreased lo the extent of one-half, while the
                  production has increased by two- thirds and upwards. Chemical science has applied
                  itself to this manufacture with much success in this country, and the best soap is
                  produced at a rate very inferior to that of indifferent soaps in other countries,
                  and in our own at a former period. </p>

               <p xml:id="e29"> The candle manufacture is also conducted on a very large scale. The introduction
                  of oil, camphine, gas,, and other means of giving light, does not appear to have
                  very materially influenced this manufacture. The cause of which may, perhaps, be
                  sought in tho reluctance of many to apply gas to household users, and in the
                  convenience of the use of a solid instead of a fluid material for domestic lights.
                  Chemistry has effected much for this manufacture. By its aid a new material has
                  been introduced which has become a most extensive substitute for wax and
                  spermaceti, not only in this but also in foreign countries. Fiscal restrictions
                  having been removed, the improvement in the candle manufacture has been most
                  striking, and the benefit to the public and to commerce proportionate. </p>

               <p xml:id="f29"> The minor articles comprised within the limits of tins (-lass do not receive
                  fishing-tackle, &amp;e.,hnve all (heir re8iH.'ctiye importance, and may, by those
                  interested in them, be studied in the locality already named. — <persName ref="#RE">R.
                     E.</persName>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
