<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Gia-Alexander/HIST630/master/RebuiltODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TEI Encoding of the Introduction to Class 24 from <bibl><title> Volume III of the
                     Official Catalogue of the Great Exhibition of the Works of Industry of All
                     Nations <date when="1851">1851</date>(4 vols.),</title><biblScope unit="page"
                     from="697" to="698"/></bibl></title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Gia O. Alexander</authority>
            <pubPlace>College Station, TX</pubPlace>
            <date>Fall 2019</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                  Licence and may be freely reused with attribution.</licence>
               <p>The primary source material for this project is available in the public domain at
                  archive.org.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the publication of the source work. Introductions to sections of
               the catalogue containing information about about writing substrates, implements and
               accessories excerpted from <bibl><title>Volume III of the Official Catalogue of the
                     Great Exhibition of the Works of Industry of All Nations <date
                        when="1851">1851</date></title> (4 vols.) from
                  <publisher>Archive.org</publisher>, scanned from <placeName ref="#HarvardCollege">Harvard College
                     Library</placeName> by <publisher>Google Books</publisher>. <idno type="URI">
                     https://archive.org/details/officialcatalog06unkngoog/page/n14</idno></bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <category xml:id="Glass">
                  <catDesc>
                     GLASS
                  </catDesc>
                  <category xml:id="Windows">
                     <catDesc>A. Window-glass, including Sheet-glass, Crown-glass, and Coloured Sheet-glass</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="StainedGlass">
                     <catDesc>B. Painted, and other kinds of ornamented Window-glass</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="CastGlass">
                     <catDesc>C. Cast plate-glass</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Bottles">
                     <catDesc>D. Bottle-glass</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="ChemGlass">
                     <catDesc>E. Glass for Chemical and Philosophical Apparatus</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="FlintGlass">
                     <catDesc>F. Flint-glass, or Crystal, with or without lead, white, coloured, and ornamented
                        for Table Vases, &amp;c.</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="OpticalGlass">
                     <catDesc>G. Optical Glass, Flint and Crown.
                        <idno type="URI">https://www.pinterest.com/0dzfvk5cc28d7wk/antique-magnifying-glasses/?autologin=true</idno>
                     </catDesc>
                  </category>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="class" n="3.24">
            <head type="class">GLASS</head>
            <div type="intro">
               <head type="subTitle"> INTRODUCTION. </head>

               <p xml:id="a24"> The beautiful and valuable production, which forms the subject of the present
                  Class and its subdivisions, is beginning to assume an extraordinary degree of
                  importance id the present day. Yet few manufactures have, until within a very
                  recent period, made so small an amount of progress. Every process of the
                  manufacturer having been beset with the stringent regulations considered to be
                  necessary to enforce the due observance of ho Excise laws, and no exemption being
                  permitted even for the purposes of experiment or improvement, it is scarcely a
                  matter of surprise that the production of glass remained in a poor and imperfect
                  state both as a manufacture and as a philosophical problem. The same causes now no
                  longer existing, a vast amount of progress baa been made both in the extension of
                  the applications of this product, and also in the processes of its manufacture. </p>

               <p xml:id="b24"> Considered philosophically, the Class resolves itself into the following
                  subdivisions: — A. Window-glass, including Sheet-glass, Crown-glass, and Coloured
                  Sheet-glass ; B. Painted, and other kinds of ornamented Window-glass ; C. Cast
                  plate-glass ; D. Bottle-glass; E. Glass for Chemical and Philosophical Apparatus;
                  F. Flint-glass, or Crystal, with or without lead, white, coloured, and ornamented
                  for Table Vases, &amp;c. ; G. Optical Glass, Flint and Crown. </p>

               <p xml:id="c24"> The position in the Building where articles in this Class will be sought is in
                  the Central North Gallery, where an extremely beautiful and interesting collection
                  of various articles in glass is displayed. Immediately above these articles, and
                  suspended from the girders of the roof, are large and costly chandeliers, of great
                  magnificence of appearance, and in white and coloured crystal-glass. But in
                  other parts of the Building various large objects belonging (o this Class are
                  arranged, as in the Transept and Main Avenues. The size of these will not fail to
                  render them appreciable to the visitor. the whole Building may, in fact, be
                  regarded as a display of the powers of the manufacturers of this country to
                  produce rapidly, and from apparently exhaustless resources, this beautiful
                  material. </p>

               <p xml:id="d24"> As the glass, forming so large a portion of the Exhibition Building is of
                     <placeName ref="#Birmingham">Birmingham</placeName> production, it may be reasonably imagined
                  that from this town the largest contributions of glass have been forwarded. This
                  glass manufacture being extensive in this place, has become developed to an
                  enormous degree after (he removal of The Excise restrictions in <date when="1845">1845</date>. Formerly
                  glass was made in <placeName ref="#Birmingham">Birmingham</placeName> only by large manufacturers,
                  but now the commoner kinds of blown and pressed glass are produced in large
                  quantities by persons having only a small amount of capital, manufacturing on a
                  limited scale, at a cheap rate, and requiring a rapid conversion of the proceeds
                  of their little furnaces into money. The glass thus produced is of the most
                  inferior kind, and would only find a sale in consequence of its marvellous
                  cheapness. The works of the great manufacturers are on the most splendid and
                  extensive scale, and in them the manufacture of this strictly chemical product is
                  carried on upon a truly philosophic basis, and on the grandest commercial scale.
                  As an evidence of this may be adduced the production at one great establishment,
                  in addition to their ordinary business, of that vast surface of glass which covers
                  and protects the Building. Probably in no other country could a demand as sudden
                  and unexpected have been met with so much certainty as in the instance in
                  question. </p>

               <p xml:id="e24"> [n addition to the glass of the Building, the Great Crystal Fountain, in the
                  Transept, has its interest as a production derived from the same locality. This
                  fountain is twenty-seven feet in perpendicular altitude, and contains about four
                  tons of pure crystal glass. It is probably the largest production of its kind ever
                  made. The great specimens of plate-glass, one of which exceeds considerably the
                  size of any previous sheet of glass made jn any country, are not exclusively from
                     <placeName ref="#Birmingham">Birmingham</placeName>. <placeName ref="#StHelens">St. Helen's</placeName>,
                     <placeName ref="#Sunderland">Sunderland</placeName>, <placeName ref="#Newcastle">Newcastle</placeName>, and other
                  localities, contain large glass-works, some of which are exclusively devoted to
                  the manufacture of plate-glass, which :s a very distinct art from that of ordinary
                  glass. <objectName type="Bottles">Bottle</objectName> and chemical glass is produced on a vast scale at Stourbridge, a
                  locality possessing several natural advantages for the prosecution of
                  glass-melting. Glass-houses exist in the <placeName ref="#London">
                  Metropolis</placeName> itself, which turn out principally table and ornamental
                  glass. </p>

               <p xml:id="f24"> A most remarkable circumstance in the history of the glass manufacture is the
                  fact that, during half a century prior to the removal of the duty, notwithstanding
                  the augmentation of the population, there was actually a decrease in the quantity
                  of glass manufactured. Since <date when="1845">1845</date>, however, it has immensely
                  increased, and is daily receiving new applications, the value of the material for
                  a variety of purposes having long been recognised, but its employment being
                  rendered impossible by the excessive duties to which it was subjected, </p>

               <p xml:id="g24"> English manufacturers have lately been making important experiments with a view
                  to discover a method of producing glass free from colour, and from striae, for
                  optical purposes. Several specimens are exhibited in illustration, and appear to
                  promise favourably for the issue. The great refracting Telescope in the Nave is an
                  evidence that large achromatic glasses, nearly a foot in diameter, are capable of
                  being produced from English glass. Hitherto much of the optical glass has been
                  derived from abroad. It is a gratifying fact that already glass is beginning to be
                  actually exported for the use of continental opticians, and it is sometimes
                  reimported at a higher rate into <placeName ref="#England">England</placeName>, under the assumed
                  title of foreign glass. Successful attempts to imitate the beautiful art of the
                  Venetians in ornamental glass have lately been made, and specimens are exhibited.
                  New and patented processes of silvering glass, not with mercury, but with a
                  deposit of pure silver, receive a variety of beautiful illustrations in different
                  objects. </p>

               <p xml:id="h24"> It would be difficult to name another material which could, with any advantage,
                  take the place of glass in its domestic, economical, and philosophical purposes.
                  The facility of its manipulation, combined with the beauty of the material, and
                  the perfect applicability to the purposes for which it is designed, render this
                  manufacture one of the most interesting, and probably ultimately among the most
                  important, of this country. England possesses great facilities for the production
                  of the best glass, on the largest scale and at the cheapest rate. In her natural
                  stores of fuel, in her commercial resources of alkali, and in the possession of
                  the requisite capital to enter largely into this branch of industry, this country
                  appears to require nothing beyond a short space of time to assume one of the first
                  positions in the manufacture of glass. And the variety of interesting facts which
                  become daily linked with the process of this art, appear to leave little doubt
                  that, ere long, glass will be substituted for many of the materials used in the
                  economy of our dwellings, and probably for their construction also. — <persName  ref="#RE">R.
                  E.</persName>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
