<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
   <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TEI Encoding of the Introduction to Class 26 from <bibl><title> Volume III of the
                     Official Catalogue of the Great Exhibition of the Works of Industry of All
                     Nations <date when="1851">1851</date>(4 vols.),</title><biblScope unit="page"
                     from="729" to="729"/></bibl></title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Gia O. Alexander</authority>
            <pubPlace>College Station, TX</pubPlace>
            <date>Fall 2019</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                  Licence and may be freely reused with attribution.</licence>
               <p>The primary source material for this project is available in the public domain at
                  archive.org.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the publication of the source work. Introductions to sections of
               the catalogue containing information about about writing substrates, implements and
               accessories excerpted from <bibl><title>Volume III of the Official Catalogue of the
                     Great Exhibition of the Works of Industry of All Nations <date
                        when="1851">1851</date></title> (4 vols.) from
                  <publisher>Archive.org</publisher>, scanned from <placeName ref="#HarvardCollege">Harvard College
                     Library</placeName> by <publisher>Google Books</publisher>. <idno type="URI">
                     https://archive.org/details/officialcatalog06unkngoog/page/n14</idno></bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <category xml:id="Furniture">
                  <catDesc>
                     FURNITURE, UPHOLSTERY, PAPER HANGINGS, PAPIER MACHE AND JAPANNED GOODS
                  </catDesc>
                  <category xml:id="Decor">
                     <catDesc>A. Decoration generally, including Ecclesiastical Decoration</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Upholstery">
                     <catDesc>B, Furniture Upholstery</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Wallpaper">
                     <catDesc>C. Paper-hangings</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="PapierMache">
                     <catDesc>D. Papier mache. Japanned Goods, Pearl, and Tortoiseshell work.
                        <idno type="URI">https://www.pinterest.com/spdaut/antique-victorian-papier-mache/</idno>
                     </catDesc>
                  </category>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="class" n="3.26">
            <head type="class"> FURNITURE, UPHOLSTERY, PAPER HANGINGS, PAPIER MACHE AND JAPANNED
               GOODS. </head>
            <div type="intro">
               <head type="subTitle"> INTRODUCTION. </head>

               <p xml:id="a26"> The objects contemplated by the present Class are such as pertain to decorative
                  and domestic uses in the furniture exclusively of this description. All those
                  articles fur which the wants or luxuries of mankind have created a demand are
                  represented in this Class, and a lively picture of the degree of social and
                  domestic refinement attained in our age, and also, in fact, of the application of
                  art to ordinary objects, is thus presented to view. The Class is a large one in
                  regard to the number of its Exhibitors, and also to the space occupied in the
                  Exhibition Building. The articles exhibited present evidences of a large
                  expenditure of time and money, and many of the decorative objects appear better to
                  become the apartments of a palace than those of persons in the ordinary walks of
                  life. </p>

               <p xml:id="b26"> The Class is thus subdivided : — A. Decoration generally, including
                  Ecclesiastical Decoration ; B, Furniture ]il Upholstery ; C. Paper-hangings ; D.
                  Papier mache. Japanned Goods, Pearl, and Tortoiseshell work. In the Building,
                  articles belonging to this Class will be found arranged in Areas I. J. 19 to 25,
                  and L. to O, 21 to 24. These Areas will be readily found ou the South side of the
                  Eastern Nave, midway between the Transept and the Western Entrance. Several
                  specimens of furniture are exhibited among the objects in the Fine Art Court. The
                  immense mirrors in the Avenue, which may be considered, when mounted in decorated
                  frames. as belonging to this Class, occupy a prominent position, which must render
                  them appreciable to every visitor. other articles, such as a Corinthian capital in
                  papier mache, a pianoforte, and a table in the same material, are likewise placed
                  in the Western Main Avenue. The paper-hangings are placed on the wall at the
                  North-east corner of the Building, on the Ground Floor, and in the Gallery above.
                  The wall decorations, imitation marbles and woods, blinds, &amp;c, are placed
                  against the principal walls and partitions of the Building the South side, East
                  and West ends, North-east corner, and in the Locomotive Avenue. In the Court,
                  called the Medieval Court, are also a collection of articles included in this
                  Class. </p>

               <p xml:id="c26"> The number of different localities producing such articles as are comprised
                  within this Class is, as might be expected, very considerable, although a large
                  proportion, from causes readily intelligible, is derived from the Metropolis. The
                  production of most of the objects of furniture, presenting few mechanical
                  difficulties, and being universally felt to be necessary, is carried on in almost
                  every locality in this kingdom. But some of those articles which relate to
                  decoration, as pa|)cr-hangings, are generally made in the larger manufacturing
                  towns only. Of late, Manchester has produced a large number of paper-hangings,
                  printed by machinery ; in the Metropolis, a higher but more expensive class of
                  paper-hanging is made principally by ink, or, in other terms, by block-printing.
                  The manufacture of papier mache is carried on to a very large extent at 
                  Birmingham, where extensive factories have been erected, which are devoted solely to
                  the production of a variety of objects in this useful material. The manufacture is
                  also carried on at <placeName ref="#Southampton">Southampton</placeName> and in the
                     <placeName ref="#London">Metropolis</placeName>. </p>

               <p xml:id="d26"> The amount of ingenuity, of contrivance, and arrangement, which has been expended
                  upon furniture, is scarcely conceivable, and it has been applied to the moat
                  common objects of domestic utility. Tables, couches, chairs, &amp;c., have all
                  received a share of this kind of attention ; and those improvements in their
                  adaptation to use, which have been considered worthy of more extensive
                  introduction, are illustrated in different directions, Many specimens of
                  furniture, formed out of timber of extreme antiquity, are exhibited. Furniture Is,
                  also, shown, the material of which is new in its application to such purposes — as
                  timber from New Zealand, &amp;c. The beautiful varieties of veining im mahogany,
                  walnut, oak, and other woods, arc admirably illustrated in different pieces of
                  furniture exhibited. </p>

               <p xml:id="e26"> Glass has lately been applied with some success in imitation of marble for the
                  purposes of decoration. The under surface is painted with the colours and veins of
                  marble, and the effect seen from above is not dissimilar, a variety of
                  paper-hangings of different designs, and of decorations applied to apartments,
                  are also exhibited. The paper mache articles are extremely beautiful, and the
                  manner in which they are inlaid with pearl is interesting. </p>

               <p xml:id="f26"> The appearance of the entire Class bespake a high degree of national prosperity ;
                  and, while displaying the skill and taste of the manufacturers, indicates not less
                  distinctly the wealth and domestic refinement of those for whose use the greater
                  majority of the articles exhibited are unquestionably intended. — <persName ref="#RE">R.
                  E.</persName>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
