<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>TEI Encoding of the Introduction to Class 23 from <bibl><title> Volume III of the
                     Official Catalogue of the Great Exhibition of the Works of Industry of All
                     Nations <date when="1851">1851</date>(4 vols.),</title><biblScope unit="page"
                     from="671" to="671"/></bibl></title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Gia O. Alexander</authority>
            <pubPlace>College Station, TX</pubPlace>
            <date>Fall 2019</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                  Licence and may be freely reused with attribution.</licence>
               <p>The primary source material for this project is available in the public domain at
                  archive.org.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the publication of the source work. Introductions to sections of
               the catalogue containing information about about writing substrates, implements and
               accessories excerpted from <bibl><title>Volume III of the Official Catalogue of the
                     Great Exhibition of the Works of Industry of All Nations <date when="1851"
                        >1851</date></title> (4 vols.) from <publisher>Archive.org</publisher>,
                  scanned from <placeName ref="#HarvardCollege">Harvard College Library</placeName> by <publisher>Google
                     Books</publisher>. <idno type="URI">
                     https://archive.org/details/officialcatalog06unkngoog/page/n14</idno></bibl>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy>
               <category xml:id="Metal">
                  <catDesc>
                     WORKS IN PRECIOUS METALS, JEWELLRY, ETC. 
                  </catDesc>
                  <category xml:id="Communion">
                     <catDesc>A. Communion Services</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="PreciousMetals">
                     <catDesc> B, Articles of Gold and Silver Plate fur decorative purposes, and Presentation Pieces</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="GeneralDomestic">
                     <catDesc>C. Smaller Articles for more general domestic use</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="ElectroPlate">
                     <catDesc>D. Electro-plated Goods of all descriptions, comprehending all that can be executed in Silver and other Metals</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="SheffieldPlate">
                     <catDesc>E. Sheffield and other Plated Goods</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Ormolu">
                     <catDesc>F. Gilt and Ormolu Work
                        <idno type="URI">https://www.1stdibs.com/furniture/decorative-objects/desk-accessories/inkwells/material/ormolu/</idno>
                     </catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Jewellery">
                     <catDesc>G. Jewellery, inclusive of Precious Stones and Ornaments worked in Ivory, Jet, Sec.</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="OrnamentsToys">
                     <catDesc>H. Ornaments and Toys, worked in Iron, Steel, and any other
                        metal, which are neither precious metals nor imitations of them, as Chatelains of
                        Steel, Chains of Steel, Sword-hilts, Cut-steel Shoe and Knee Buckles, &amp;c.</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Enamel">
                     <catDesc>I. Enameling and Damascene Work</catDesc>
                  </category>
                  <category xml:id="Curios">
                     <catDesc>J. Articles of use or curiosity not included in the previous Sub-Classes. </catDesc>
                  </category>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="class" n="3.23">
            <head type="class"> WORKS IN PRECIOUS METALS, JEWELLRY, ETC. </head>
            <div type="intro">
               <head type="subTitle"> INTRODUCTION. </head>

               <p xml:id="a23"> The present Class comprises objects of great attractiveness to almost every
                  individual. The opportunity they afford for the display of taste and skill, and
                  even of a high description of art, combined with the intrinsic beauty and value of
                  the material in which these objects are wrought, makes them an extremely
                  interesting study. It Is impossible, also, other considerations being disregarded,
                  to suppress a feeling of surprise and admiration at tbe massive character of many
                  of the articles in this Class, indicating the wealth and resources of the
                  manufacturers. As an instance may be mentioned, a solid silver table-top,
                  fifty-five inches in diameter, and weighing nearly nine hundred ounces. But when
                  it is considered that upon the reduction of the unshapen metal into its present
                  form, the artist and mechanic have both been occupied, and that the result is to
                  indicate not less the talent of the one than the industrial skill of the other,
                  these objects, whatever their size or intrinsic value, assume, in proportion to
                  the degree of talent and labour employed in their manufacture, a new and higher
                  value. </p>

               <p xml:id="b23"> This Class is divisible into the following Sub-Classes : — A. Communion Services
                  ; B, Articles of Gold and Silver Plate fur decorative purposes, and Presentation
                  Pieces ; C. Smaller Articles for more general domestic use ; D. Elect
                  Electro-plated Goods of all descriptions, comprehending all that can be executed
                  in Silver and other Metals : E. Sheffield and other Plated Goods ; P. Gilt and
                  Ormolu Work ; G. Jewellery, inclusive of Precious Stones and Ornaments worked in
                  Ivory, Jet, Sec. ; H. Ornaments and Toys, worked in Iron, Steel, and any other
                  metal, which are neither precious metals nor imitations of them, as Chatelains of
                  Steel, Chains of Steel, Sword-hilts, Cut-steel Shoe and Knee Buckles, &amp;c. ; I.
                  Enameling and Damascene Work ; and J. Articles of use or curiosity not included in
                  the previous Sub-Classes. </p>

               <p xml:id="c23"> The general position in the Building o the articles in this Class is in the South
                  Central Gallery. After passing from the cases containing lace and embroidery,
                  proceeding westward, these which contain the articles in the precious metals arc
                  met with, and extend from M. 6 to 22. But several objects properly belonging to
                  this Class, and included in it, are exhibited, as in other instances, in other
                  parts of the Building ; the Jewel- case and the Great Diamond exhibited by
                     <persName ref="#QueenVictoria">Her Majesty</persName> are instances of this
                  description. </p>

               <p xml:id="d23"> Articles in the precious metals are produced in almost all large towns, and those
                  exhibited are consequently derived from a number of different lucidities. In the
                  metropolis very large and wealthy firms exist, producing annually large quantities
                  of silver goods, upon some of which great expenses are incurred, in order to give
                  to them the character of art-productions. Since the introduction of the beautiful
                  art of electro-plating, <placeName ref="#Birmingham">Birmingham</placeName> has supplied very large
                  quantities of silver and electro-plated articles, and a number of extensive
                  factories exist in that town, in which this strictly chemical operation is
                  practiced on a grand and commercial scale. In Sheffield the process of plating by
                  fire, that is, by the soldering a plate of silver on an ingot of copper by means
                  of heat, rolling out and fashioning for use, has long been successfully pursued.
                  It has been established that the value of the British-made plate annually used in
                  this country amounts to 1,200,000 lb, and the exports of plate, jewellry, &amp;c,
                  amounted to the value of 233,058L. </p>

               <p xml:id="e23"> All these varieties in the manufacture of objects of use and luxury included in
                  this Class will be found illustrated by the productions of different exhibitors,
                  by many of whom a gorgeous display of plate and jewels is made. Attention cannot
                  fail to be directed to the great Diamond, the Koh-i-Noor ; and to the Jewel-case
                  in the Cinque-Cento style, exhibited by <persName>Her Majesty The
                  Queen</persName>. In addition is a table of gold and silver electro- plate, which
                  is an interesting reproduction of an antique subject. The massive specimens of
                  presentation plate exhibited will likewise receive due notice. Among the jewels
                  are several interesting and perhaps unique specimens ; one of the latter is a
                  large blue diamond weighing 177 grains. -- <persName  ref="#RE">R. E.</persName>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
